you're beginning to be able to do that with life. It means that we're beginning to learn how to read this language. And this, of course, is the language that is used by this orange. So how does this orange execute code? It doesn't do it in ones and zeroes like a computer does. It sits on a tree, and one day it does: plop! And that means: execute. AATCAAG: make me a little root. TCGACC: make me a little stem. GAC: make me some leaves. AGC: make me some flowers. And then GCAA: make me some more oranges. If I edit a sentence in English on a word processor, then what happens is you can go from this word to that word. If I edit something in this orange and put in GCAAC, using CRISPR or something else that you've heard of, then this orange becomes a lemon, or it becomes a grapefruit, or it becomes a tangerine. And if I edit one in a thousand letters, you become the person sitting next to you today. Be more careful where you sit. (Laughter) What's happening on this stuff is it was really expensive to begin with. It was like long-distance calls. But the cost of this is dropping 50 percent faster than Moore's law. The first $200 full genome was announced yesterday by Veritas. And so as you're looking at these systems, it doesn't matter, it doesn't matter, it doesn't matter, and then it does. So let me just give you the map view of this stuff. This is a big discovery. There's 23 chromosomes. Cool. Let's now start using a telescope version, but instead of using a telescope, let's use a microscope to zoom in on the inferior of those chromosomes, which is the Y chromosome. It's a third the size of the X. It's recessive and mutant. But hey, just a male. And as you're looking at this stuff, here's kind of a country view at a 400 base pair resolution level, and then you zoom in to 550, and then you zoom in to 850, and you can begin to identify more and more genes as you zoom in. Then you zoom in to the state level, and you can begin to tell who's got leukemia, how did they get leukemia, what kind of leukemia do they have, what shifted from what place to what place. And then you zoom in to the Google street view level. So this is what happens if you have colorectal cancer for a very specific patient on the letter-by-letter resolution. So what we're doing in this stuff is we're gathering information and just generating enormous amounts of information. This is one of the largest databases on the planet and it's growing faster than we can build computers to store it. You can create some incredible maps with this stuff. You want to understand the plague and why one plague is bubonic and the other one is a different kind of plague and the other one is a different kind of plague? Well, here's a map of the plague. Some are absolutely deadly to humans, some are not. And note, by the way, as you go to the bottom of this, how does it compare to tuberculosis? So this is the difference between tuberculosis and various kinds of plagues, and you can play detective with this stuff, because you can take a very specific kind of cholera that affected Haiti, and you can look at which country it came from, which region it came from, and probably which soldier took that from that African country to Haiti. Zoom out. It's not just zooming in. This is one of the coolest maps ever done by human beings. What they've done is taken all the genetic information they have about all the species, and they've put a tree of life on a single page that you can zoom in and out of. So this is what came first, how did it diversify, how did it branch, how large is that genome, on a single page. It's kind of the universe of life on Earth, and it's being constantly updated and completed. And so as you're looking at this stuff, the really important change is the old biology used to be reactive. You used to have a lot of biologists that had microscopes, and they had magnifying glasses and they were out observing animals. The new biology is proactive. You don't just observe stuff, you make stuff. And that's a really big change because it allows us to do things like this. And I know you're really excited by this picture. (Laughter) It only took us four years and 40 million dollars to be able to take this picture. (Laughter) And what we did is we took the full gene code out of a cell -- not a gene, not two genes, the full gene code out of a cell -- built a completely new gene code, inserted it into the cell, figured out a way to have the cell execute that code and built a completely new species. So this is the world's first synthetic life form. And so what do you do with this stuff? Well, this stuff is going to change the world. Let me give you three short-term trends in terms of how it's going to change the world. The first is we're going to see a new industrial revolution. And I actually mean that literally. So in the same way as Switzerland and Germany and Britain changed the world with machines like the one you see in this lobby, created power -- in the same way CERN is changing the world, using new instruments and our concept of the universe -- programmable life forms are also going to change the world because once you can program cells in the same way as you program your computer chip, then you can make almost anything. So your computer chip can produce photographs, can produce music, can produce film, can produce love letters, can produce spreadsheets. It's just ones and zeroes flying through there. If you can flow ATCGs through cells, then this software makes its own hardware, which means it scales very quickly. No matter what happens, if you leave your cell phone by your bedside, you will not have a billion cell phones in the morning. But if you do that with living organisms, you can make this stuff at a very large scale. One of the things you can do is you can start producing close to carbon-neutral fuels on a commercial scale by 2025, which we're doing with Exxon. But you can also substitute for agricultural lands. Instead of having 100 hectares to make oils or to make proteins, you can make it in these vats at 10 or 100 times the productivity per hectare. Or you can store information, or you can make all the world's vaccines in those three vats. Or you can store most of the information that's held at CERN in those three vats. DNA is a really powerful information storage device. Second turn: you're beginning to see the rise of theoretical biology. So, medical school departments are one of the most conservative places on earth. The way they teach anatomy is similar to the way they taught anatomy 100 years ago. "Welcome, student. Here's your cadaver." One of the things medical schools are not good at is creating new departments, which is why this is so unusual. Isaac Kohane has now created a department based on informatics, data, knowledge at Harvard Medical School. And in a sense, what's beginning to happen is biology is beginning to get enough data that it can begin to follow the steps of physics, which used to be observational physics and experimental physicists, and then started creating theoretical biology. Well, that's what you're beginning to see because you have so many medical records, because you have so much data about people: you've got their genomes, you've got their viromes, you've got their microbiomes. And as this information stacks, you can begin to make predictions. The third thing that's happening is this is coming to the consumer. So you, too, can get your genes sequenced. And this is beginning to create companies like 23andMe, and companies like 23andMe are going to be giving you more and more and more data, not just about your relatives, but about you and your body, and it's going to compare stuff, and it's going to compare stuff across time, and these are going to become very large databases. But it's also beginning to affect a series of other businesses in unexpected ways. Normally, when you advertise something, you really don't want the consumer to take your advertisement into the bathroom to pee on. Unless, of course, if you're IKEA. Because when you rip this out of a magazine and you pee on it, it'll turn blue if you're pregnant. (Laughter) And they'll give you a discount on your crib. Right? So when I say consumer empowerment, and this is spreading beyond biotech, I actually really mean that. We're now beginning to produce, at Synthetic Genomics, desktop printers that allow you to design a cell, print a cell, execute the program on the cell. We can now print vaccines real time as an airplane takes off before it lands. We're shipping 78 of these machines this year. This is not theoretical biology. This is printing biology. Let me talk about two long-term trends that are coming at you over a longer time period. The first one is, we're starting to redesign species. And you've heard about that, right? We're redesigning trees. We're redesigning flowers. We're redesigning yogurt, cheese, whatever else you want. And that, of course, brings up the interesting question: How and when should we redesign humans? And a lot of us think, "Oh no, we never want to redesign humans." Unless, of course, if your child has a Huntington's gene and is condemned to death. Or, unless if you're passing on a cystic fibrosis gene, in which case, you don't just want to redesign yourself, you want to redesign your children and their children. And these are complicated debates and they're going to happen in real time. I'll give you one current example. One of the debates going on at the National Academies today is you have the power to put a gene drive into mosquitoes so that you will kill all the malaria-carrying mosquitoes. Now, some people say, "That's going to affect the environment in an extreme way, don't do it." Other people say, "This is one of the things that's killing millions of people yearly. Who are you to tell me that I can't save the kids in my country?" And why is this debate so complicated? Because as soon as you let this loose in Brazil or in Southern Florida -- mosquitoes don't respect walls. You're making a decision for the world when you put a gene drive into the air. This wonderful man won a Nobel Prize, and after winning the Nobel Prize he's been worrying about how did life get started on this planet and how likely is it that it's in other places? So what he's been doing is going around to this graduate students and saying to his graduate students, "Build me life but don't use any modern chemicals or instruments. Build me stuff that was here three billion years ago. You can't use lasers. You can't use this. You can't use that." He gave me a vial of what he's built about three weeks ago. What has he built? He's built basically what looked like soap bubbles that are made out of lipids. He's built a precursor of RNA. He's had the precursor of the RNA be absorbed by the cell and then he's had the cells divide. We may not be that far -- call it a decade, maybe two decades -- from generating life from scratch out of proto-communities. Second long-term trend: we've been living and are living through the digital age -- we're starting to live through the age of the genome and biology and CRISPR and synthetic biology -- and all of that is going to merge into the age of the brain. So we're getting to the point where we can rebuild most of our body parts, in the same way as if you break a bone or burn your skin, it regrows. We're beginning to learn how to regrow our tracheas or how to regrow our bladders. Both of those have been implanted in humans. Tony Atala is working on 32 different organs. But the core is going to be this, because this is you and the rest is just packaging. Nobody's going to live beyond 120, 130, 140 years unless if we fix this. And that's the most interesting challenge. That's the next frontier, along with: "How common is life in the universe?" "Where did we come from?" and questions like that. Let me end this with an apocryphal quote from Einstein. [You can live as if everything is a miracle, or you can live as if nothing is a miracle.] It's your choice. You can focus on the bad, you can focus on the scary, and certainly there's a lot of scary out there. But use 10 percent of your brain to focus on that, or maybe 20 percent, or maybe 30 percent. But just remember, we really are living in an age of miracle and wonder. We're lucky to be alive today. We're lucky to see this stuff. We're lucky to be able to interact with folks like the folks who are building all the stuff in this room. So thank you to all of you, for all you do. (Applause)
nous pourrons bientôt faire tout ça avec le vivant aussi. Nous sommes en train d'apprendre à lire cette langue. Voici le langage de cette orange. Comment l'orange exécute-t-elle son code ? Pas comme un ordinateur, avec des uns et des zéros. Elle est sur l'arbre, et un jour : pouf ! Ça signifie : exécution ! AATCAAG : fais une petite racine ! TCGACC : fais un petit germe ! GAC : fais des feuilles ! AGC : fais des fleurs ! Ensuite GCAA : fais des oranges ! En éditant une phrase en anglais sur un traitement de texte, on peut naviguer d'un mot à l'autre. En amendant une partie dans cette orange, en utilisant CRISPR pour remplacer GCAAC par autre chose de connu, l'orange devient un citron, un pamplemousse ou une mandarine. En modifiant une seule lettre parmi mille, vous devenez votre voisin. Choisissez vos voisins avec prudence ! (Rires) À ses prémisses, la technologie était très coûteuse, comme les appels longue distance. Mais le coût diminue plus vite que la loi de Moore par un facteur de 50%. Hier, Veritas a annoncé le premier séquençage du génome pour 200 dollars. On observe ces systèmes et ils n'ont aucune importance jusqu'à ce qu'ils deviennent importants. Voici une cartographie de ce dont nous parlons. Une découverte énorme. Il y a 23 chromosomes. Cool. Regardons-les avec la version télescopique mais en remplaçant le télescope par un microscope pour zoomer sur le chromosome du bas, le chromosome Y. Il est trois fois plus petit que le X, récessif et mutant. Mais... c'est juste un mâle. Quand on observe tout ça, on est au niveau d'une carte d'un pays, une résolution de 400 paires de bases, on zoome à 550, ensuite à 850. Là, on commence à identifier de plus en plus de gènes. En zoomant davantage, on obtient une carte régionale. On peut identifier les personnes qui souffrent de leucémie, comment elles l'ont eue et quel type de leucémie, quelles parties ont glissé vers où. On zoome un peu plus et on en est à Google Street View. Voici ce qui se passe pour un patient bien déterminé qui a un cancer du côlon à un niveau de résolution lettre par lettre. Nous collectons en fait des informations et générons un volume énorme de données. C'est une des plus grandes banques de données au monde et sa croissance dépasse notre capacité à construire des espaces pour leur stockage. On peut créer des cartes incroyables avec ça. Pour comprendre la peste, et pourquoi une espèce est bubonique une autre est d'un autre type, et une autre est encore différente. Voici la cartographie de la peste. Certaines sont implacablement mortelles pour l'homme, d'autres pas. Pour approfondir, pourquoi pas comparer la peste à la tuberculose ? Voici la différence entre la tuberculose et différentes espèces de peste. On peut faire un travail de détective en prenant par exemple une espèce précise du choléra qui a touché Haïti. On peut rechercher le pays à son origine, la région même et sans doute aussi le soldat qui l'a emmenée d'Afrique à Haïti. Dézoomons. Aller vers le plus petit n'est pas tout. Voici une des cartes les plus cool réalisées par l'homme. On a repris toutes les informations génétiques connues sur toutes les espèces et on a compilé ça sur un arbre de vie qui tient sur une page. On peut zoomer et dézoomer. Voici ce qui est venu en premier, sa diversification, son rayonnement et la taille de ce génome. Tout ça sur une seule page. C'est l'univers du vivant sur la Terre, mis à jour et complété constamment. Dans cette évolution de la biologie, le changement fondamental est qu'avant, la biologie était réactive. Les biologistes avaient des microscopes et des loupes pour observer les animaux. La nouvelle biologie est proactive. On ne fait pas qu'observer, on crée aussi des choses. C'est une révolution car ça nous permet de réaliser des choses comme ceci. Je suis persuadé que cette photo vous enthousiasme. (Rires) Cette photo nous aura demandé quatre ans de travail et 40 millions de dollars. (Rires) Qu'avons-nous fait ? On a retiré un génome complet d'une cellule, pas un gène, pas deux gènes, mais le génome complet de la cellule, pour construire un nouveau code génétique, l'insérer dans une cellule et trouver un moyen que cette cellule exécute notre code pour développer une nouvelle espèce. Il s'agit donc de la première forme de vie synthétique. Que fait-on avec ça ? Le monde de demain ne sera plus jamais pareil. Les trois premières tendances sur le court terme qui vont transformer le monde sont les suivantes. Tout d'abord, il y aura une nouvelle révolution industrielle. Au sens littéral du terme. Tout comme la Suisse, l'Allemagne et la Grande-Bretagne ont changé le monde avec des engins comme ceux exposés dans le hall d'entrée, en générant l'électricité, tout comme le CERN est en train de transformer le monde, avec des instruments nouveaux et notre conception de l'univers, les formes de vie programmables vont changer le monde car dès qu'il est possible de programmer une cellule, tout comme on programme une puce électronique, alors tous devient possible. Votre puce électronique peut produire des images, de la musique, des films, des lettres d'amour ou des tableaux de calcul. Tout ça est fait de zéros et de uns. Si on peut encoder des ATCG dans les cellules, le logiciel va créer sa propre machine. En d'autres mots, il va se développer rapidement. Quoi qu'il arrive, en abandonnant votre portable à votre chevet, vous ne vous retrouverez pas avec un milliard de portables le lendemain. Mais avec des organismes vivants, on parle d'échelles incroyables. Une des choses devenues possibles est par exemple la production de combustibles neutres au niveau de l'impact carbone, à une échelle commercialisable dès 2025. Nous travaillons sur ça avec Exxon. On peut aussi remplacer les terres agricoles. Plutôt que d'exploiter 100 hectares pour produire de l'huile ou des protéines, on peut les produire dans des cuves avec un rendement variant entre 10 et 100 fois celui d'un hectare. On peut aussi y stocker l'information ou y fabriquer les vaccins pour le monde. On pourrait même stocker toutes les informations du CERN dans ces bassins. L'ADN offre des possibilités de stockage considérables. Deuxième changement : voici l'avènement de la biologie théorique. Les facultés de sciences médicales sont un des lieux les plus conservateurs au monde. On y enseigne l'anatomie aujourd'hui exactement comme il y a 100 ans : « Bonjour à tous. Voici votre cadavre. » Les écoles de médecine sont particulièrement médiocres quand il s'agit de créer de nouveaux départements et le font rarement. Isaac Kohane a créé un département fondé sur les données, les connaissances, à la Harvard Medical School. Dans un sens, la biologie commence à collecter assez de données pour suivre les pas de la physique. C'est-à-dire que de physique d'observation et d'expérimentation, elle est devenue créatrice, physique théorique. C'est en train d'arriver en biologie car nous avons toutes ces données médicales et toutes ces données sur les gens : leurs génomes, leurs viromes et leurs microbiomes. Plus les informations s'accumulent, plus on peut réaliser des prédictions. La troisième transformation est que le consommateur est touché. Vous aussi, vous pouvez obtenir un séquençage de vos gènes. Cela mène à la création d'entreprises comme 23andMe. Ces entreprises comme 23andMe pourront vous offrir de plus en plus d'informations, sur les membres de votre famille, sur vous, sur votre corps. Elles proposeront de comparer des données, leur évolution dans le temps et cela produira des bases de données massives. D'autres domaines d'activités sont aussi affectés de manière inattendue. Quand on fait une publicité, le but n'est pas que le consommateur emporte votre publicité aux toilettes pour uriner dessus. Sauf si vous vous appelez IKEA. Si vous déchirez cette publicité de votre magazine pour uriner dessus, elle devient bleue si vous êtes enceinte. (Rires) L'annonceur vous offre un rabais sur l'achat d'un berceau. OK ? Quand je parle d'émancipation des consommateurs, et cela va au-delà des biotechnologies, je pense ce que je dis. À Synthetic Genomics, nous sommes en train de développer des imprimantes portables qui vous permettent de concevoir une cellule, de l'imprimer et d'exécuter un programme dans la cellule. Aujourd'hui, on peut imprimer des vaccins en temps réel quand un avion décolle et avant qu'il atterrisse. Cette année, on va livrer 78 de ces imprimantes. Ce n'est plus de la biologie théorique, c'est de la biologie imprimée. Permettez-moi d'évoquer deux tendances à long terme qui vont arriver sur une longue période. D'abord, nous sommes en train de modifier les espèces. Vous avez dû en entendre parler. On modifie des arbres, des fleurs, du yaourt, du fromage et tout ce que vous voulez. Ceci entraîne une question fascinante : comment et quand devrions-nous amender les humains ? Nous sommes nombreux à penser : « Jamais nous ne voudrons ça ! » Sauf si votre enfant a le gène de Huntington et est condamné à mourir. Sauf si vous êtes porteur du gène de la mucoviscidose et, dans ce cas, vous souhaiterez un amendement pour vous et aussi pour vos enfants et leurs enfants. Il s'agit de débats complexes et ils ont lieu maintenant. Un exemple : un des débats en cours dans les Académies nationales concerne notre capacité à provoquer une mutation génétique chez les moustiques qui tuera tous les moustiques porteurs de la malaria. Certains pensent que l'impact sur l'environnement mérite d'agir avec précaution. D'autres, toutefois, pensent que cette maladie tue des millions de personnes tous les ans. On ne peut pas nous empêcher de sauver les enfants de nos pays. Pourquoi ce débat est-il si complexe ? Parce qu'en lâchant ça au Brésil, ou au sud de la Floride, les moustiques n'ont pas de frontières. C'est une décision qui affecte le monde entier que de libérer une mutation génétique. Cet homme extraordinaire a reçu le Prix Nobel. Suite à son Prix Nobel, il s'est intéressé à comment la vie a démarré sur cette planète et à la probabilité de la trouver ailleurs. Aujourd'hui, il passe son temps avec ses étudiants en leur demandant ceci : « Créez une vie mais sans aucun produit chimique ou instrument modernes. Créez quelque chose qui existait il y a trois milliards d'années. Sans lasers. Sans ceci. Sans cela. » Il m'a donné une fiole avec ce qu'il a fabriqué il y a trois semaines. Qu'est-ce que c'est ? Il a fabriqué ce qui ressemble à des bulles de savon faites de lipides. Il a fabriqué un précurseur de l'acide ribonucléique. Il a fait absorber ce précurseur d'ARN par une cellule qu'il a laissée se diviser. On pourrait ne pas être loin, on parle de dix ou vingt ans, du moment où nous pourrons générer la vie à partir de rien, à partir de proto-communautés. Deuxième tendance sur le long terme : nous sommes en train de vivre dans l'ère numérique, nous faisons nos premiers pas dans l'ère du génome. La biologie, CRISPR, la biologie synthétique et tout le reste vont se réunir dans l'ère du cerveau. Nous arrivons à l'étape où nous pouvons régénérer la plupart de nos organes telle la guérison de la peau ou d'un os après une brûlure ou une fracture. Nous apprenons à régénérer nos trachées et nos vessies. On en a implanté chez des humains. Tony Atala développe 32 organes différents. Mais ceci va devenir le cœur car c'est vous, et le reste n'est qu'une enveloppe charnelle. Personne ne vivra au-delà de 120, 130 ou 140 ans. Sauf si nous réglons ça. C'est aussi le défi le plus intéressant. C'est la nouvelle frontière, avec : « La vie est-elle généralisée dans l'univers ? » « D'où venons-nous ? » entre autres. Je conclurai avec une citation apocryphe d'Einstein. [Il n'y a que deux façons de vivre sa vie : faire comme si tout était un miracle ou rien n'était un miracle] C'est votre choix. Vous pouvez vous focaliser sur le mauvais et l'effroyable, et il y a certes des choses effrayantes. Mais utilisez 10 ou 20% de votre cerveau à ça, voire 30%. Surtout, rappelez-vous, nous vivons dans une ère de miracle et d'émerveillement. Nous avons la chance de vivre maintenant et d'être les témoins de tout ça. Nous avons la change d'interagir avec des personnes comme celles qui construisent toutes ces choses et qui sont parmi nous. Merci à vous tous pour ce que vous faites. (Applaudissements)